Finding Aid for Albert J. Schimpke collection of R.G. Peters materials, 1890-circa 1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Albert J. Schimpke collection of R.G. Peters materials
1890-circa 1970
Schimpke, Albert J., 1899-1985, collector
88142 Aa 2; UAm
The Albert J. Schimpke collection consists of photographs, audio-tapes, and other materials collected by Mr. Schimpke relating to Manistee, Michigan, especially the activities of one of its most prominent local lumbermen, Richard G. Peters.
4 linear feet in 6 boxes
1 oversize folders
173 GB
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Helen S. Thomas and Burton J. Schimpke (donor no. 7393 ) and came to the library in two accession, October 1986 and November 1987.
The collection is open to research.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
Richard G. Peters was born on July 2, 1832 in Delaware county, New York. His parents, James H. and Susan Squires Peters, moved their family from the farm where R.G. Peters was born to Cincinnati, Ohio and Syracuse, New York, where they were employed as hotelkeepers. When his mother died in 1847, R.G. Peters moved to Tully, New York to live with his grandparents and where he worked as a gatekeeper on a toll road for his uncle.
In 1850, at the age of eighteen, Peters returned to the Midwest and was employed in the engineering department of the Michigan Southern Railroad Company. He served as assistant engineer in charge of a division of the road for five years.
Peters became involved with the lumber industry in 1855 when he managed the lumber and mill of Charles Mears at Big Point au Sable. He held this position for five years until he purchased a small tract of government land in order to do his own lumbering. This venture was abandoned, however, when he became superintendent for the next two years at James Ludington's mill and lumber operations in what is now the town of Ludington. During these early efforts to get established in the lumbering industry, he married Evelyn N. Tibbets of Oberlin, Ohio on April 6, 1862.
In 1866, Peters purchased the Filer and Tyson mill and timber property with M. S. Tyson and G. W. Robinson. The purchase included the sawmills on Manistee Lake and most of the site of the city of Manistee. In 1869, he bought the Wheeler and Hopkins mill on Manistee Lake, which he operated for the next thirteen years before it burned down. He also added forty acres and a mill on East Lake to his holdings. The old mill was rebuilt and a new one added. Salt was discovered in the area and became another Peters' venture. The Manistee and Luther Railroad, with its approximately eighty miles of track between East Lake and LeRoy, Osceola county, was part of Peters' operation.
In 1869, Peter purchased two large tracts of land near Manistee and established the town of Tallman. These two new acquisitions contained 130,000,000 board feet of pine. He also bought the mill property and salt block at Ludington and thirty miles of logging road. Peters' timber holdings in Michigan and Wisconsin were established at 150,000 acres with an additional 100,000 acres in Florida. Peters was known as "King among lumbermen." In addition to being president of the R. G. Peters Salt and Lumber Company, the Manistee and Luther Railroad, and Peters Lumber and Shingle Company of Benton Harbor, he served as vice-president of Butters and Peters Salt and Lumber Company of Ludington and the Batchelor Cyprus Lumber Company with holdings in Florida. He was director in the Manistee National Bank, the Michigan Salt Association, and the Manistee (Furniture) Manufacturing Company.
Evelyn Peters died on February 14, 1879. R.G. Peters married Janet Telford of Onekama, Michigan on June 15, 1898. He had no children from either marriage. His date of death is not known.
The Albert J. Schimpke collection of R.G. Peters materials contains papers, photographs, negatives, and audio-tapes of interviews largely relating to lumbering in Manistee, Michigan.
Subjects:
Logging--Michigan--Manistee.; Lumbering--Michigan--Manistee.; Manistee (Mich.); Peters, Richard G., b. 1832.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Aged persons.; Bear Lake (Mich.); Benton Harbor (Mich.); Boats.; Butcher shops.; Cooks.; Dining rooms.; Eastlake (Mich.)--Industrial buildings.; Eastlake (Mich.)--Salt industry.; Grocery stores.; Industrial buildings--Michigan--Eastlake.; Interiors.; Laborers.; Lumber industry.; Manistee (Mich.); Mills.; Peters, Richard G., b. 1832.; Peters family.; Peters Salt & Lumber Company.; Railroad accidents.; Railroad bridges.; Railroad construction and maintenance.; Railroad handcars.; Railroad shops and yards.; Railroads--Michigan.; Salt industry--Michigan--Eastlake.; Schools--Michigan.; Weddings.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Schimpke, Albert J., 1899-1985.; Lumbering--Michigan.; Manistee (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Aerial photographs.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Collected Papers
  The first series, Collected Papers, contains four folders. Included is a collection of newspaper clippings of a series called "Manistee Yesteryears," which appeared in the Manistee newspaper during the 1950s. There is also in this series a list of locomotives of the Manistee and Northeastern Railway Company. This list specifies original owners, builders, dates built, dates of purchase, cylinder sizes, engine weight, numbers of flues and sizes, wheel bases, tractive power, diameters of driving wheel centers, and remarks. The folder also contains a history of the Manistee and Northeastern Railway. This pamphlet is largely illegible but does contain a good map of the railroad and its connections.
  - Peters estate (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, circa 1952-1954 (Box 1)
  - Manistee and Northeastern Railway Company materials, circa 1956 (Box 1)
- Photographs, circa 1890-1915
  The second series - Photographs, ca. 1890-1915 - comprises the bulk of the collection. This series consists of prints and negatives collected by Schimpke from various donors who were involved or whose relatives were involved in Peters' operations. Although there is some relationship between several photographs and negatives in this collection, the photographs are neither numbered nor otherwise identified and are difficult to match with their negatives. The photographs have been, therefore, organized according to subject matter. Most of these images are of logging and railroad scenes. The railroad scenes depict the transporting of logs by rail, locomotives, handcars, and various train scenes. Portraits of Peters, his wife Evelyn and his brother William and employee group portraits are included. Scenes of logging camps, mills, salt and lumber plants and towns are also included as well as a folder on boats, one of which was Peters' yacht. Within this series, there are also 260 negatives and two glass negatives. This part of the collection is arranged numerically, with a few unnumbered negatives in the back. There are gaps in the numbering sequences. Most of the negatives have information on their envelopes. This often includes the name of the donor, the date of the donation, the subject, photographic developing information, and remarks. The remarks can be detailed and, in some cases, identify many of the subjects. Since most of the photographs are not identified, information on the negative jackets can be quite useful.
  - Portraits of R.G. Peters, wife (Evelyn?) (Box 1)
    (see also oversize folder UAm)
  - Other portraits, brother William, family members, etc. (Box 1)
  - Group portraits of employees (Box 1)
    (see also oversize box 3)
  - Town scenes
    - Buildings and interiors (Box 1)
    - Aerial views (Box 1)
  - Logging camps
    - Logging camp scenes (Box 1)
    - Dining room interiors (Box 1)
  - Mill scenes (Box 1)
  - Salt and Lumber plants
    - Panoramic views (Box 1)
      (see also oversize box 3 and oversize folder UAm)
    - Interiors (Box 1)
  - Boats (Box 1)
    (see also photograph of Peters' yacht in box 3)
  - Logging scenes, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Transporting logs by rail, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Locomotives, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Train wreck (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous train scenes (Box 1)
  - Handcars (Box 1)
  - Train trusses (Box 1)
  - Machine shop and Manistee and Northeastern Railway Company round house (Box 1)
  - Dedication of post office, Manistee (?) (Box 1)
    (in oversize box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Logging scenes, group portraits of employees, trains, boats, company shops (Box 3)
    (oversize photos; contents listed above)
  - Photonegatives, 260 negatives approximate number (Box 2)
    (donor-produced listing of contents filed with negatives)
  - Glass negatives, 2 photographs (Box 2)
- Sound recordings
  The series Sound recordings consists of taped interview by Schimpke with associates of Peters. These interview were recorded on ca. 58 reel-to-reel tapes. In 1994-1995, seventy-five cassette use copies of these tapes were made.
  - Digital Audio Files
    [Digitized audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.]
    - George Albertson; Carl Hedstrom; Emil Winters, 1962 August 01; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-1-1]; mp3 file; (Discussion of railroading in Michigan in the early 20th century from former railroad workers.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-1-2]; mp3 file; (Discussion of railroading in Michigan in the early 20th century from former railroad workers.)
    - Stanley Allen; Charles Vincent, 1956 August 14, 1957 October 16; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-2-1]; mp3 file; (Stanley Allen interviewed on August 14, 1957, discussion of lumbering in Northern Michigan in the late 19th and early 20th centuries.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-2-2]; mp3 file; (Charles Vincent interviewed on October 16, 1957, discussion of lumbering in Northern Michigan in the late 19th and early 20th centuries.)
    - Mrs. Gage Avery; Jim Carboneau, 1960 November 07-08; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-3-1]; mp3 file; (1960 November 07, interview with Mrs. Gage Avery, daughter of a lumberman in Northern Michigan.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-3-2]; mp3 file; (1960 November 08 interview with Jim Carboneau, resident of Manistee discussing the lumber mills and railroading in the early 20th century.)
    - Jim Carboneau, 1960 November 08; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-4-1]; mp3 file; (Interview with Jim Carboneau, resident of Manistee discussing the lumber mills and railroading in the early 20th century.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-4-2]; mp3 file; (Interview with Jim Carboneau, resident of Manistee discussing the lumber mills and railroading in the early 20th century.)
    - Jim Carboneau, 1954 October 27; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-5-1]; mp3 file; (Part 1; Interview with Jim Carboneau, resident of Manistee discussing the lumber mills and railroading in the early 20th century.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-5-2]; mp3 file; (Part 1; Interview with Jim Carboneau, resident of Manistee discussing the lumber mills and railroading in the early 20th century.)
    - Jim Carboneau, 1954 October 27; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-6-1]; mp3 file; (Part 2; Interview with Jim Carboneau, resident of Manistee discussing the lumber mills and railroading in the early 20th century.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-6-2]; mp3 file; (Interview with Jim Carboneau, resident of Manistee discussing the lumber mills and railroading in the early 20th century.)
    - Axel Carlson; William Sytek, 1954 November 10, 12; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-7-1]; mp3 file; (Axel Carlson interviewed on November 10, 1954, discussing railroading in Northern Michigan and loading of lumber trains.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-7-2]; mp3 file; (William Sytek interviewed November 12 1954, interview discussing lumbering in Northern Michigan.)
    - Mrs. (Anna) Andrew Carlson, Hoxeyville, 1st half, 1956 September 19; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-8-1]; mp3 file; (Part 1; Interview on the subject of life in Northern Michigan (Manistee area) in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
    - Emory Dumas, 1955 January 18; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-9-1]; mp3 file; (Discussion of farm history in Northern Michigan.)
    - Robert Fox; Clarence Warner, 1955 January 06-07; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-10-1]; mp3 file; (1955 January 07 interview and discussion on farming and lumbering in the Manistee area.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-10-2]; mp3 file; (1955 January 06 interview and discussion farming, lumbering, and the railroads in the Manistee area.)
    - Robert Fox, 1955 January 11; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-11-1]; mp3 file; (Part 2; Interview on the subject of life in Northern Michigan (Manistee area) in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
    - Walter Goff, 1955 February 18; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-12-1]; mp3 file; (Part 1; Interview on the subject of railroading in Northern Michigan (Manistee area) in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-12-2]; mp3 file; (Part 2; Interview on the subject of railroading in Northern Michigan (Manistee area) in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
    - W. H. Green; Andre Johnson in error, 1954 February 02; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-13-1]; mp3 file; (Interview on the subject of railroading and lumbering in Northern Michigan (Manistee area) in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-13-2]; mp3 file; (Interview on the subject of railroading and lumbering in Northern Michigan (Manistee area) in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
    - Emil Hansen; Carl H. Hansen, 1956 October 20, 22; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-14-1]; mp3 file; (Emil Hansen interviewed on October 20,1956. Interview on the subject of railroading and lumbering in Northern Michigan (Manistee area) in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-14-2]; mp3 file; (Carl H. Hansen interviewed on October 22, 1956. Interview on the subject of railroading and lumbering in Northern Michigan (Manistee area) in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
    - Pete Hardy; Laban Peters, 1955 October 05, 11; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-15-1]; mp3 file; (Pete Hardy interviewed on October 5, 1955. Interview on the subject of railroading and lumbering working conditions in Northern Michigan (Manistee area) in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-15-2]; mp3 file; (Laban Peters interviewed on October 11, 1955. Interview on the subject of railroading and lumbering working conditions in Northern Michigan (Manistee area) in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
    - Esther Holmes and Matilda Holmes, 1956 November 05; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-16-1]; mp3 file; (Interview on the subject of R.G. Peter's wife from her workers in Northern Michigan (Manistee area) in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
    - Sofus “Tom” Jensen, 1960 September 21; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-17-1]; mp3 file; (Interview with Sofus "Tom" Jensen, born in Denmark discussing life in the Manistee area. (1st half))
    - Warren Jensen; Frank Jones and Clyde White, 1057 October 17; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-18-1]; mp3 file; (Interview with Warren Jensen (front half); Frank Jones, Clyde White (2/3 of back) on the subject of life in Northern Michigan (Manistee area) in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-18-2]; mp3 file; (Interview with Warren Jensen (front half); Frank Jones, Clyde White (2/3 of back) on the subject of life in Northern Michigan (Manistee area) in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
    - Andre Johnson; Axel Carlson, 1954 November 04, 10; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-19-1]; mp3 file; (Andre Johnson interviewed November 04, 1954, 1st half and last 2/3; Axel Carlson November 10, 1954, last 1/3; Interview on the coming of the railroad in the Manistee area in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-19-2]; mp3 file; (Andre Johnson interviewed November 04, 1954, 1st half and last 2/3; Axel Carlson November 10, 1954, last 1/3; Interview on the coming of the railroad in the Manistee area in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
    - Oscar Larson, GR&I Railroad, Hal Cutler, 1954 October 01, 12-13; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-20-1]; mp3 file; (Oscar Larson interviewed October 01, 1954, GR&I Railroad interview October 12, 1954, Hal Cutler interviewed October 13, 1954; Interview on the coming of the railroad in the Manistee area in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-20-2]; mp3 file; (Oscar Larson interviewed October 01, 1954, GR&I Railroad interview October 12, 1954, Hal Cutler interviewed October 13, 1954; Interview on the coming of the railroad in the Manistee area in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
    - Jay Lee, 1955 January 06; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-21-1]; mp3 file; (Reel 1; Interview on the coming of the railroad in the Manistee area in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-21-2]; mp3 file; (Reel 1; Interview on the coming of the railroad in the Manistee area in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
    - Jay Lee, 1955 January 06; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-22-1]; mp3 file; (Reel 2; Interview on the coming of the railroad in the Manistee area in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-22-2]; mp3 file; (Reel 2; Interview on the coming of the railroad in the Manistee area in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
    - Jay Lee, 1955 January 06; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-23-1]; mp3 file; (Reel 3; Interview on the coming of the railroad in the Manistee area in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-23-2]; mp3 file; (Reel 3; Interview on the coming of the railroad in the Manistee area in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
    - Russell H. Lee, 1954 December 18; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-24-1]; mp3 file; (Interview on the railroad and lumbering business in the Manistee area in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-24-2]; mp3 file; (Interview on the railroad and lumbering business in the Manistee area in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
    - Locomotive, [Undated]; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-25-1]; mp3 file; (Recording of locomotive sounds, no other content.)
    - John Lusher, 1956 November 06; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-26-1]; mp3 file; (Interview on the ship wrecks and the coats in Northern Michigan in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-26-2]; mp3 file; (Interview on the ship wrecks and the coats in Northern Michigan in the late 19th and early 20th century.)
    - Hans Madison, 1956 November 06; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-27-1]; mp3 file; (Interview with Hans Madison, born in 1874 in Denmark who worked in Mills and Railroads in the Manistee area.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-27-2]; mp3 file; (Interview with Hans Madison, born in 1874 in Denmark who worked in Mills and Railroads in the Manistee area.)
    - Martha, 1st half, 1961 March 15; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-28-1]; mp3 file; (Interview with Martha, born in Germany. Portions of her interview are in German.)
    - George Morehead; Warren and Thomas Benson, 1955 November 04, 06; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-29-1]; mp3 file; (George Morehead interviewed November 04, 1954. Interviews discussing the railroad and lumbering industries in the Manistee area.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-29-2]; mp3 file; (Warren and Thomas Benson interviewed November 06 1955; Interviews discussing the railroad and lumbering industries in the Manistee area.)
    - Eugene Otto; Sam Granger; August Steffens, 1956 November 09, 13; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-30-1]; mp3 file; (Eugene Otto interviewed November 09, 1956, Sam Granger interviewed November 09, 1956. August Steffens interviewed November 13 1956. Interviews discussing the railroad and lumbering industries in the Manistee area.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-30-2]; mp3 file; (Eugene Otto interviewed November 09, 1956, Sam Granger interviewed November 09, 1956. August Steffens interviewed November 13 1956. Interviews discussing the railroad and lumbering industries in the Manistee area.)
    - Roy Overpack; Joseph Fisk; John Lusher, 1956 September, October 26; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-31-1]; mp3 file; (Roy Overpack; Joseph Fisk interviewed in September of 1956. John Lusher interviewed October 26,1956. Interviews discussing the railroad and lumbering industries in the Manistee area.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-31-2]; mp3 file; (Roy Overpack; Joseph Fisk interviewed September of 1956. John Lusher interviewed October 26,1956. Interviews discussing the railroad and lumbering industries in the Manistee area.)
    - Laban Peters, 1955 November 11; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-32-1]; mp3 file; (Reel 2; Interviews discussing the business of the railroad and lumbering industries in the Manistee area.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-32-2]; mp3 file; (Reel 2; Interviews discussing the business of the railroad and lumbering industries in the Manistee area.)
    - Laban Peters, 1956 August 28; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-33-1]; mp3 file; (Reel 3; Interviews discussing the business of the railroad and lumbering industries in the Manistee area.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-33-2]; mp3 file; (Reel 3; Interviews discussing the business of the railroad and lumbering industries in the Manistee area.)
    - Laban Peters, 1956 August 28; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-34-1]; mp3 file; (Reel 4; Interviews discussing the business of the railroad and lumbering industries in the Manistee area.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-34-2]; mp3 file; (Reel 4; Interviews discussing the business of the railroad and lumbering industries in the Manistee area.)
    - Chris Peterson and Amanda Peterson, 1956 November 07; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-35-1]; mp3 file; (Interview with Chris Peterson and Amanda Peterson. Additional paper materials in the tape box.)
      - [Part 2], [88142-SR-35-2]; mp3 file; (Interview with Chris Peterson and Amanda Peterson. Additional paper materials in the tape box.)
    - Minnie Johnson Erickson Ramsey; Mrs. Emil Swanson; Anna Anderson, 1957 September 04, October 22; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [88142-SR-36-1]; mp3 file; (Minnie Johnson Erickson Ramsey interviewed September 04, 1957, 2/3 front side; Mrs. Emil Swanson interviewed October 22, 1957, 1/3 front side; Anna Anderson; Interviewing Manistee residents about R.G. Peters and his contributions to the region.)